Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Memory Project Collection AD.RG.023
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Interviews with NYUAD Community Members [during Covid], Spring 2020 - Summer 2022
  - Interview session with Malak Abdel-Ghaffar, Sara Pan Algarra, Alicja Borzyszkowska, Ian Hoyt (ElevatED), and Lauren Kata (44:44), 07 May 2020; ADRG023_014 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_014)
    In this interview, NYUAD students Malak Abdel-Ghaffar, Sara Pan Algarra, Alicja Borzyszkowska, and Ian Hoyt reflect on their experiences as parts of the Student Interest Group (SIG) ElevatED, and in particular about their recent project: the children's book 'Where Is Our Home?' They tell the stories behind their involvement with ElevatED and the book in particular. They also share the process behind the book, such as brainstorming for ideas on the train in Turkey or drafting the book at Starbucks. They reflect on their first reactions to the printed book, and the obstacles they had to overcome to complete the project.
  - Interview session with Peter Dicce (Athletics) and Lauren Kata (01:17:38), 02 Jun 2020; ADRG023_015 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_015)
    Video-recorded session with Peter Dicce, Assistant Dean of Students and Director of Athletics, recorded on June 2, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project. Recordings and transcripts are preserved in the NYUAD University Archives. Coach Peter Dicce reflects on his journey to NYU Abu Dhabi, from practicing law in the United States, to leading the Department of Athletics in NYUAD. He talks about building the department from a few students and informal teams, to getting uniforms, and then later becoming leaders in collegiate sports in the country. A major reason for this success comes from a concerted effort to create and build a community among students, coaches, and administrators, which was achieved through creating traditions and breaking down gender or social barriers. He describes the enjoyable process of creating more friendly competition and interaction through ADISL [Abu Dhabi Inter-University Sports League], as well as creating a logo and mascot for NYUAD, both of which encouraged neighbouring schools to participate. Coach Dicce fondly remembers the origins of many traditions such as the Sports Majlis, the semesterly Falcon Feast, Interclasico, and Defend the Nest.
  - Interview session with Aicha Zekar, Eyob Mengiste, Pantelis Demetriou (Engineering Instructors), and Lauren Kata (01:35:25), 02 Jul 2020; ADRG023_017 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_017)
    Video-recorded session with Pantelis Demetriou, Instructor of Mechanical Engineering; Eyob Mengiste, Instructor of Civil Engineering; and Aicha Zekar, Associate Instructor of Civil Engineering, recorded on 2 July, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project.
    Aicha reflects on her journey at NYUAD after joining the institution in 2016 alongside Eyob and Pantelis who were both part of the Global Academic Fellow (GAF) Program and are now instructors. Due to the nature of their instructor role, they describe their interesting experiences leading labs and creating experiments, which Eyob and Pantelis state have become more innovative since 2014. Aicha touches on the role of class size in forging closer connections with her students, which is also reflected in the wider community as they observe that there is a close-knit community amongst the instructors across departments, and between them and NYUAD's contracted staff, for example. Eyob and Pantelis describe their experiences in the GAF Program, which provided close communication channels between themselves and students, as well as inter-departmental connections. Additionally, they praise the J-term courses and the Engineers for Social Impact (EFSI) program for facilitating academic and personal growth through travel and opportunities to connect with many different types of people.
  - Interview session with Phillip Panicker (Engineering/ERB) and Lauren Kata (01:24:06), 07 Jul 2020; ADRG023_018 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_018)
    Video-recorded session with Phillip Panicker, Senior Lecturer and Coordinator of Engineering Academic Laboratories at NYUAD, recorded on 7 July, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library.
    In this interview, Phillip Panicker discusses the early days of the Engineering program, the transition to the Saadiyat Campus, and the development of the Engineering for Social Impact (EFSI) program. Having grown up in the UAE, Panicker discusses his engineering background and how he became involved in logistics and teaching at NYUAD'S Center for Science and Engineering in Mussafah. He discusses the study projects, social experiences, and dining options available for those in the early Engineering program, and how they transitioned into wider traditions. He recounts the journey of NYUAD from an unimpressive and unknown program, to a hallmark institution of the city. The final half of the interview focuses on the development of the EFSI program. Proud of what the program has become, Panicker discusses its values, logistics, and evolution as realized by students, faculty, and staff.
  - Interview session with Jim McGrath (Athletics) and Lauren Kata (01:04:27), 08 Jul 2020; ADRG023_019 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_019)
    Video-recorded session with Jim McGrath, Manager for Community Sports and Campus Recreation, recorded on 8 July, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Jim McGrath discusses his journey from a stay-at-home dad and volunteer flag football coach to Community Sports and Campus Recreation Manager at NYU Abu Dhabi. Recounting his first spontaneous contact with NYUAD and Wayne Young in 2012, McGrath discusses the close community of the early DTC along with the many challenges establishing an athletics program without its own venues in the UAE. Centering the student experience and the role of athletics in the NYUAD community, McGrath shares humorous and exciting memories that highlight the inclusivity and spontaneity of student involvement. The later portions of the interview focus on NYUAD's role in building the inter-collegiate athletics scene in the UAE with a special emphasis on increasing the opportunities for female athletics not just within NYUAD, but across all the schools with which NYUAD cooperates and competes. McGrath concludes the interview by sharing about the bonds he has built with his students and those the students have built with each other through the Athletics program.
  - Interview session with Amos Katz (Equipment Center/A&H) and Lauren Kata (01:43:04), 08 Jul 2020; ADRG023_020 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_020)
    Video-recorded session with Amos Katz, Lecturer and Technical Manager of the Arts and Media at NYU Abu Dhabi, recorded on 8 July, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Katz discusses his history with the NYUAD Arts program, specifically through his relationship with the Equipment Center. Coming from NYU Tisch and Singapore, Katz recounts the exciting energy and "pioneering spirit" of the early years of NYUAD. He tells the stories of the many challenges of setting up the Arts program at the DTC, specifically the logistics of procuring and managing Arts equipment. The interview also touches on struggles with loneliness and the challenges of feeling integrated into the city. Katz goes on to discuss the complicated challenges involved in moving to the Saadiyat campus, building the spaces and systems that define the present day Arts program – such as the Equipment Center -- and its relationship to the Library in particular. Throughout the interview Katz makes an effort to name all the people he worked with and express gratitude towards them.
  - Interview session with Lyne Ismail (Athletics) and Lauren Kata (01:10:28), 21 Jul 2020; ADRG023_021 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_021)
    Video-recorded session with Lyne Ismail, Athletic Administration and Special Projects Coordinator, and Head Coach of the Women's Soccer Team, recorded on 21 July, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project.
    Lyne reflects on her journey with NYU Abu Dhabi Athletics, something she was heavily encouraged to do by Wayne Young even through the interview phase. She talks about the immense support she received from the department that felt more like a family, as she was able to attain her coaching certification while coaching the Women's Soccer Team. Her current role (at the time of the interview) is focused on the management of many traditional Athletic events like Interclasico, Falcon Feast and Defend the Nest. She was instrumental in the creation of SoccHer then leading to HerSports, which is able to connect NYU Abu Dhabi to the wider community. Overall, she is proud of the inclusion she has witnessed in sports within the region especially with regard to the Special Olympics and the popularity of women in sports.
  - Interview session (Part 1) with Hafsa Ahmed, Vongai Mlambo, Zain Mustafa, Motoi Oyane, Lier Qiu (StuGov AY2019-2020), and Lauren Kata (01:27:38), 10 Aug 2020; ADRG023_022 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_022)
    Video-recorded session with NYUAD students Hafsa Ahmed, Vongai Mlambo, Zain Mustafa, Motoi Oyane, and Lier Qiu, recorded on Monday, 10 August 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, recent graduates and members of the Executive Board of the Student Government -- Hafsa, Vongai, Zain, Motoi and Lier -- reflect on their time at NYUAD. They each share their first impressions of the campus and their favorite memories and challenges, ranging from their Candidate Weekend experiences and birthday celebrations to J-term courses, football games and First Year Writing Seminar. They talk about their motivations and roles in Eboard and discuss their journeys as members of the StuGov. The students also talk about the biggest issues the StuGov had to face during their participation, as well as the changes they made in the community. Finally, they discuss the hardest moments of their time in the StuGov Eboard.
  - Interview session with Zain Mustafa, Guillermo Andres Schlamp (Marhaba) and Lauren Kata (01:49:23), 07 Sep 2020; ADRG023_023 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_023)
    Video-recorded session with Zain Mustafa and Guillermo Andres Schlamp, members of the Marhaba Team at NYU Abu Dhabi, recorded on Monday, 7 September, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Zain and Guillermo reflect on their experiences as the long-term members of the Marhaba Team at NYUAD. They share their motivations behind joining the team, and their views on the goals, values, and structure of Marhaba and its role in the NYUAD community. They reflect on their personal memories in the team, and explain how Marhaba has changed over the years. At the same time, they name several Marhaba events that have stayed the same, such as Marhaba Dinner, Speed Chatting, and Talent Show. Zain and Guillermo discuss ways to encourage community-building on campus and navigating the interests of the student body and administration when welcoming first-year students.
  - Interview session with Samer Madanat (Engineering, Deans) and Lauren Kata (01:26:10), 08 Sep 2020; ADRG023_024 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_024)
    Video-recorded session with NYUAD Dean of Engineering Samer Madanat, recorded on Tuesday, 8 September, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Madanat recounts his engineering career, integration into the NYUAD Engineering Division, and efforts to expand and refine the division for the long-term goals of the University. After discussing his relationship to the Middle East and his time at Berkley, Madanat discusses his perspectives on transportation, engineering, and how those perspectives manifested in his work at NYUAD. Discussing the Division's expansion – particularly with a focus on the creation of the Bio-Engineering program – Madanat recounts anecdotes of intradivision and interdisciplinary cooperation. Impressed by many of his students, Madanat likewise speaks highly of the undergraduates he taught.
  - Interview session (Part 2) with Hafsa Ahmed, Vongai Mlambo, Zain Mustafa, Lier Qiu (StuGov Eboard AY2019-2020) and Lauren Kata (42:18), 18 Sep 2020; ADRG023_025 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_025)
    Video-recorded session with NYUAD students Hafsa Ahmed, Vongai Mlambo, Zain Mustafa and Lier Qiu, recorded on Friday, 18 September, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    Recent graduates Hafsa, Vongai, Zain and Lier reflect on their experiences as members of the Executive Board of the Student Government during the COVID-19 pandemic. They each discuss the challenges they had to face in those unprecedented times and the issues and students' concerns they had to prioritize. Some of those include navigating their conflicting roles and interests as simultaneously students and the StuGov members, maintaining a healthy work-life balance and advocating for students while avoiding the development of their dependency on the StuGov.
  - Interview session with Siba Siddique (Class of 2018) and Lauren Kata (29:10), 23 Oct 2020; ADRG023_026 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_026)
    Video-recorded session with Siba Siddique class of 2018, recorded on 23 October, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    Siba Siddique reflects on her time at NYU Abu Dhabi as the first class to spend all four years on the Saadiyat campus. She describes NYUAD as a tight-knit community, in which she was able to take part through her many Foundations of Science classes, her participation in the women's basketball team, Muslim Students Association and Engineers For Social Impact (EFSI) program. Siba recalls many NYUAD traditions including the midnight surprise birthday gatherings held for friends, Midnight Breakfast and the changing of the lights on the dome of the Campus Center. Even as an alumnus, the NYUAD network is strong as she is able to maintain connections with other alumni and the wider community.
  - Interview session with Krushika Patankar (Class of 2015) and Lauren Kata (34:50), 23 Oct 2020; ADRG023_027 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_027)
    Video-recorded session with Krushika Patankar Class of 2015 alumnus, recorded on 23 October, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project.
    Krushika details her experience with NYU Abu Dhabi, initially being hesitant about the institution after growing up in Oman, then later realising that NYUAD played a significant role in creating the person she has become. She became enthralled with the University after her experience at Candidate Weekend where she met peers from all over the world who had diverse languages and cultures. After coming to NYUAD her experiences with sharing food, her relationship with the dining hall staff and even the Sama fire, allowed her to feel a sense of belonging. Krushika became involved in many areas including the RealAD show, REACH, and Student Government. Krushika went through periods of adjustment, especially adapting to an American academic culture, and later adjusting to the move from downtown to the Saadiyat campus.
  - Interview session with Felix Beck (Plastics Lab) and Lauren Kata (01:26:04), 29 Nov 2020; ADRG023_028 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_028)
    Video-recorded session with Felix Beck, Former Assistant Engineering Professor of Practice of Design, recorded on 29 November, 2020 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview Felix Beck discusses his journey to join and become progressively more integrated in NYUAD's Engineering program. In particular, Beck recounts his various projects related to teaching and exploring the field of design. Sharing stories of exciting student projects, inter-department collaborations, and artistic endeavors, Beck reflects on his time at NYUAD having recently begun a new chapter in his career before the date of recording. Beck pays particular attention to his work with plastic recycling through NYUAD's Plastic Recycling Research Lab, and creative institutional navigation in pursuit of his various enterprises. Beck concludes the interview by recalling moments in campus culture that brought him joy and meaning during his time as a campus community member.
  - Interview session with Lorraine Adkins (Campus Safety) and Lauren Kata (01:28:53), 16 Dec 2020; ADRG023_029 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_029)
    Video-recorded session with Lorraine Adkins, Associate Director of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness at NYUAD, recorded on Wednesday, 16 December, 2020, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Lorraine Adkins tells her story of joining NYUAD and working with and for the community. She shares her first impressions of the UAE, and reflects on the peculiarities of ensuring community safety in the Downtown Campus and Sama Tower, and later in the new campus on Saadiyat Island. Adkins discusses the importance of teamwork in the Public Safety Department and shares the traditions and approaches for building a cohesive team. She also discusses the role of females in Public Safety and reflects on the University's preparedness for emergencies, which was recently tested by the COVID-19 Pandemic.
  - Interview session with Terry May (Equipment Center) and Lauren Kata (01:32:52), 18 Feb 2021; ADRG023_030 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_030)
    Video-recorded Memory Project session with Terry May, Assistant Manager of the Equipment Center and Instructor for Camera and Lights at NYUAD, recorded on Thursday, 18 February, 2021, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Terry May reflects on his life experiences from working as an electrician in a film industry in London to shifting to Dubai and then finally joining NYU Abu Dhabi (in 2015) as an employee in a newly operated Equipment Center. He shares how he was enthusiastic about working in the film industry right from his school days and later placed for an apprenticeship at the age of 17 in one of the biggest lighting companies in London. Later due to his medical condition and a job opportunity, he and his spouse moved to Dubai. Throughout the interview, he speaks about the growth of the Equipment Center in terms of its capacity and demands for equipment with the growing numbers of students every year. He describes his roles and responsibilities of taking account of all the associated equipment, assisting in running some film, music, and interactive media classes. He also shares his working plans and actions such as organized equipment placement/ storage systems, proper barcoding, and labeling, an accessible checkout or loan system, equipment deals (purchase and exchange) with world-class brands, etc. With the expansion of the resources and accessibility of the Equipment Center, he has also hired student assistants, who are trained closely by him via workshops and practical learning. He openly embraces that he loves to train and work with fresh minds and emphasizes the significance of a conducive working environment.
  - Interview session with Matteo Marciano, Toby Tinson, Bea Laszlo, Aaron Marcus-Willers, Ivan Budnik Pereira, Reema El Kaiali, Goffredo Puccetti, (Gazelien Records), and Lauren Kata (01:22:27), 25 Feb 2021; ADRG023_031 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_031)
    Video-recorded session with members of Gazelien Records, recorded on 25 February, 2021 and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of the Memory Project.
    Members of Gazelien Records describe their relationship with the University's student-led record label, and each other, which they describe as having a family-like feeling. Students and faculty from various disciplines, especially across the Arts, like Film and New Media, and Design, have been involved in the development of the label. The student and alumni members of Gazelien records describe the advantages of working with the label, which include training in multiple aspects of sound engineering, building a solid portfolio, dedicating long hours of work in the study and gaining cross-disciplinary knowledge. The interviewees mention how remote working has affected them, and affectionately recall working together on an important project before the University switched to remote learning in March.
  - Interview session with Laura Assanmal, Kaashif Hajee (The Gazelle) and Lauren Kata (01:16:54), 02 Mar 2021; ADRG023_032 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_032)
    Video-recorded session with Laura Assanmal and Kaashif Hajee (NYUAD Class of 2021), editors-in-chief of the student-led weekly publication The Gazelle, recorded on Tuesday, 2 March, 2021, and facilitated by Lauren Kata, Assistant Academic Librarian for Archives and Special Collections at NYUAD Library. Conducted as part of The Memory Project.
    In this interview, Laura and Kaashif reflect on their experiences as contributors and editors-in-chief of The Gazelle, the student-led weekly publication at NYUAD. They share their views on the goals, values, and structure of the publication and its role in the NYUAD community and beyond. They also discuss the peculiarities of journalist work in the context of the UAE and the diverse campus environment, including the issues of sensitivity, defamation, censorship, and relationship with the University administration. In particular, they reflect on the ideas and processes behind the creation of Issue 180 #BlackLivesMatter, dedicated to the discussions about race, inclusivity, and belonging on campus and beyond. Laura and Kaashif share the traditions existing in the team and reflect on how their work was impacted by COVID-19.
  - Interview session with Matteo Marciano, Toby Tinson, Ivan Budnik Pereira, Reema El Kaiali, Zain Mustafa, Goffredo Puccetti, (Gazelien Records Part 2) and Lauren Kata (01:25:05), 04 Mar 2021; ADRG023_033 (Box Electronic Records, Folder ADRG023_033)